Guide to the Robert Thomason Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association (PLGNA) Collection BCMS-0084
Brooklyn Collection
Robert Thomason Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association (PLGNA) Collection
1966-2016
Brooklyn Collection
Thomason, Robert
Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association
BCMS-0084
10 Linear Feet 10 document boxes, 6 legal-size document boxes, 1 oversize flat box
The collection contains materials concerning the life of Robert Thomason (1927-2020) and the activities of the Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association (PLGNA), a community-led organization founded in 1968 by Thomason and a coalition of local ministers to improve the quality of life for residents in the Prospect Lefferts Gardens neighborhood in Brooklyn, New York. The collection comprises correspondence, writings, contracts, financial documents, organizational records, flyers and brochures, newspaper clippings, photographs, and a scrapbook. The collection may be of interest to researchers studying the origins and activities of neighborhood associations and community-led grassroots organizations in Brooklyn, as well as research on housing preservation and development, discrimination in housing, redlining, gentrification, and tenants' rights. The materials in the collection range from 1966-2016.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series: Series 1: Administrative Records is arranged by subject and chronologically. Series 2: Contracts and Proposals is arranged chronologically. Series 3: Correspondence and Writing is arranged by type of record and then chronologically. Series 4: Printed Materials is arranged by type of materials and then chronologically. Series 5: Financial Records is arranged chronologically.
Biographical
Robert "Bob" Thomason was born in Crown Heights, Brooklyn in 1927 to Otey Hume and Margaret Black. Thomason grew up in Forest Hills, Queens, and later moved to Flemington, New Jersey as a teenager. He joined the army towards the end of World War II and spent time stationed in Panama. With support from the GI Bill, Thomason attended college and received a BA in Social Studies Education from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. He later attended the Yale Divinity School in New Haven, Connecticut, and became an ordained minister. In 1960, Thomason lived in Ohio and worked in the Settlement House, where he met Jane. They were married in 1960. Thomason returned to New York to attend graduate school at the Columbia School of Library Science. Thomason and his wife lived in a multi-family home in Prospect Lefferts Gardens with their two daughters, Katherine and Carolyn. They lived there for nine years before purchasing it from their landlord in 1973. He worked as a reference librarian for 20 years at the Hewlett Woodmere Public Library in Nassau County. He cycled to work 40 miles round-trip every day from Brooklyn.
In 1968, Thomason co-founded the Prospect Lefferts Garden Neighborhood Association (PLGNA) in collaboration with five ministers from the neighborhood. Thomason and his wife Jane were active members of PLGNA's board and committees throughout their lifetimes. He was also actively involved in the Lefferts Nostrand-Rogers Block Association.
After retiring from the library in 1985, Thomason became an avid cyclist taking many long bike touring trips in foreign countries, including China, Scandinavia, France, Thailand, and Japan. Robert Thomason passed away at the age of 92 at home on November 10, 2020.
Historical
The Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association (PLGNA) was founded in 1968 by Robert Thomason and a coalition of ministers looking to improve the quality of life for residents in the Prospect Lefferts Gardens neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. PLGNA was incorporated in 1969 and organized its first public program that same year, the Prospect Leffers Gardens House Tour strengthening the community by inviting neighbors into each other's homes and highlighting unoccupied homes to prospective buyers.
Through the 1970s, PLGNA and East Flatbush residents fought redlining in the neighborhood to promote a diversity of residents and effectively organized to ensure local banks invested directly into the community. From 1983 through 1994, PLGNA received grants from the New York State Division of Housing and Community Renewal and the New York City Department of Housing Preservation and Development for neighborhood preservation and redevelopment programs. Activities included revitalizing the commercial corridor, organizing street clean-ups, enlisting community members in a mobile patrol, and providing consultation to community members on housing technical assistance, including tenant court representation, block and tenant association organizing, and housing rehabilitation. PLGNA worked to get all city-owned abandoned buildings onto the market, either through private development or through a combination of private and public funding.
In 1994, PLGNA lost funding from the New York State Division of Housing and Community Renewal for breaching their contract agreement. PLGNA could no longer afford to pay its staff and closed its offices on Flatbush Avenue, suspending activities for the latter half of the 1990s. In 2000, Thomason and a group of ministers led by Reverend Ronald Winley organized to revive the organization. PLGNA was remade as a community-based, community-driven project with a new mission to reclaim and revitalize the neighborhood through positive change. In this iteration of itself, the organization added new youth and workforce development programs to its roster. Meanwhile, continuing to address affordable housing, gentrification, and displacement of residents in the Prospect Lefferts Gardens neighborhood. PLGNA hosted housing forums, art exhibitions, film screenings, community clean-ups, house tours, and an annual Martin Luther King, Jr. Day celebration. The organization is still active as of 2022.
Conditions Governing Access
Within Series 1: Administrative records and Series 5: Financial Records three folders have been identified for restriction because they contain sensitive personal information. The remainder of the collection is open for research. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert Thomason, 2016.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Thomason Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association (PLGNA) Collection is comprised of correspondence, manuscripts, contracts, financial documents, organizational records, reports, flyers and brochures, newspaper clippings, postcards, photographs, notes, and a scrapbook. The materials cover Robert Thomason's personal life and the activities of the Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association since its founding in 1968 through 2016, when the materials were donated.
The collection may be of interest to researchers studying the origins and activities of neighborhood associations and community-led grassroots organizations in Brooklyn, as well as research on housing preservation and development, discrimination in housing, redlining, gentrification, and tenants' rights.
Series 1: Administrative Records contains the association's by-laws, certificate of incorporation, annual reports, meeting minutes and agendas, five-year plans, and information about employees. These documents relate to the association's origins, including the key members involved in its founding and daily operations, chronicling the evolving mission and goals of the association from 1968 through 2016. Series 2: Contracts and Proposals consists of contractual agreements with city and state departments funding redevelopment and community programs, with the bulk of the grant-funded activity happening between 1983-1994. Granting agencies include the New York State Division of Housing and Community Renewal, the New York City Department of Housing Preservation and Development(HPD), and the New York State Department of Social Services. Extensive bookkeeping and reporting were required for HPD contracts, these summaries are included with the financial records. Series 3: Correspondence and Writing comprises correspondence to and from Robert Thomason, and board members of PLGNA, including his wife, Jane Thomason. The correspondence includes personal letters as well as communications documenting PLGNA's activities. Their is a gap in correspondence from 1993 to 1999. This series also contains writing by Robert Thomason, encompassing autobiographical writing, unpublished manuscripts, hand-written notes, and article pitches to publishers on subjects relating to racial equality, social justice, and Christianity. Series 4: Printed Material includes newsletters, flyers and programs, newspaper clippings, magazines, photographs, maps, cards, and a scrapbook. PLGNA's events and programs are represented in flyers, brochures, photographs, and PLGNA's self-published newsletter "The Good News." The series also contains flyers and brochures from other local neighborhood organizations and cultural institutions in New York City. The newspaper clippings cover neighborhood news local to Prospect Lefferts Gardens and Flatbush, relating to housing, crime, redevelopment, gentrification, and cultural events. The photographs and scrapbook in the collection document neighborhood association meetings and a street clean-up event. Series 5: Financial Records consists of a sample of the association's financial activities represented by receipts, paid vouchers, proposed budgets, financial summaries, annual financial reports, and tax filings.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Special equipment is required to view or access material stored on a DVD-R and floppy disk.
Related Materials
Ronald Shiffman collection on the Pratt Center for Community Development. Series 1: Community Planning Projects. Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association (PLGNA ), 1982-1983 (2013.023)
Brooklyn Ephemera Collection. Organizations: Prospect Lefferts Gardens Neighborhood Association, (BCMS.0007)
Brooklyn neighborhood associations and civic organizations publications, 1970-1999 (ARC.167)
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Lefferts Gardens (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Neighborhood Associations; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Citizens' associations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tenants' associations |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Series 1: Administrative Records
  - Organizational History and By-laws, 1969-2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors, 1975-2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1972-2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 2009-2014 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lefferts Nostrand-Rogers Block Association, 1979-2013 (Box 1, Folder 5-6, Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Employees, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Charitable Organization Tax Exemption Documents, 1970-1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Five-year Plans, 1985-1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Neighborhood Planning, 1969-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fundraising and Membership Dues, 1974-2006 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Surveys, 2005-2010 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Employee Timesheets RESTRICTED, 1992-1993 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Workers Compensation and Unemployment Insurance RESTRICTED, 1983-1995 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Contracts and Proposals
  - Proposals, 1978-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3-4, Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Division of Housing and Community Renewal Contracts, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Division of Housing and Community Renewal Contracts, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Division of Housing and Community Renewal Contracts, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Division of Housing and Community Renewal Contracts, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Division of Housing and Community Renewal Contracts, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Department of Housing Preservation and Development Contracts, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Department of Housing Preservation and Development Contracts, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Department of Housing Preservation and Development Contracts, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Department of Social Services (DSS) Contracts, 1991-1993 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
  - DSS Escort Service Sign-in Log, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Flatbush Development Corporation Proposal, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Youth Programs, 1993-2006 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Collective for Community, Culture, and Environment Contract, 2015 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Series 3: Correspondence and Writing
  - Correspondence, 1966-1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1990-2007 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2008-2009 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2011 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2012-2013 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2014-2015 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Robert Thomason Writings, 1966-2015 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Robert Thomason Notes, 1970-2016 (Box 8, Folder 6, Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Other Writings, 1990-2012 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Series 4: Printed Materials
  - PLGNA Flyers and Programs, 1969-2016 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - PLGNA Newsletters, 1977-2005 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Prospect Lefferts Gardens House Tour, 1977-2013 (Box 16, Folder 8, Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Other Neighborhood Organizations Flyers and Programs, 1976-2016 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - Cultural Institutions Programs, 2005-2014 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Real Estate, 1985-2006 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1968-1975 (Box 16, Folder 2-4)
  - Maps, 1970-2000 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Newspapers, 1987-2005 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1975-1999 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 2000-2014 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Magazines and Newsletters, 1976-2011 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Lefforts Manor Echo, 2005-2016 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Booklets, 2006-2009 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Community Service Award, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Business Cards, 1980-2016 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Cards and Postcards, 1990-2005 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series 5: Financial Records
  - Financial Reports, 1975-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Banking Statements and Deposits, 1985-2007 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Payroll Registers, 1985-1986 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Xeroxed Checks, 1987-1988 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Budgets, 1988-1994 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - New York State Tax Filings, 1983-1995 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Internal Revenue Service Federal Tax Filings, 1991-2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Internal Revenue Service Offer in Compromise, 1994-2001 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Receipts, 1990-2005 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Paid Vouchers, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 1-5)
  - Paid Vouchers, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
  - Paid Vouchers, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 6, Box 15, Folder 4-5)
  - Department of Housing Preservation and Development Payments and Expenses, 1991-1995 (Box 5, Folder 2-5)
  - Cash Flow Loan Program, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)